A Guide to the Thomas Fauntleroy Ball Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Thomas Fauntleroy Ball papers 1825-1961
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12711-a
This collection consists of ca. 265 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was made a gift to the University on August 12, 1966 by Mrs. Thomas Fauntleroy Ball.
Biographical/Historical Information
University of South Carolina, B.S., electrical engineering, University of Virginia, M.S.,1919; University of Virginia Instructor, Adjunct Professor and Assistant Professor of Physics, 1916-1922; also, taught at the University of South Carolina and headed the physics dept., United States Naval Academy.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, 1825-1961, contains ca. 265 items, including correspondence, printed material, and various awards of Thomas Fauntleroy Ball, a University of Virginia graduate and professor of physics. These papers record his Navy service, his tenure as an employee at Hughes Aircraft Company, and some early genealogical records.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged in alphabetical order; oversized materials are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Bank Book of Judge T. T. Fauntleroy 1884, 1922-1923, 1 item
- Certificates and Awards 1915-1955, 7 items
  July 1943, Red Cross certificate to Mary Minor Ball [by Franklin Delano Roosevelt]; November 6, 1946, Certificate of Satisfactory Service to Thomas Fauntleroy Ball. Signed by James Forrestal, Secretary of the Navy; [1946], Certificate of Appreciation to Thomas Fauntleroy Ball. Issued by Harry S. Truman.
- Genealogy 1825-[1918], 3 items
  May 26, 1825, will of Bettie S. Fauntleroy; October 12, 1897, "In Memoriam. Doctor Robert Randolph Ball"; November 5, [1918], genealogical listing.
- Hughes Aircraft Company--Business Papers and Correspondence 1959-1961, 87 items
  Correspondence, cheque receipts, and miscellaneous papers from Thomas Fauntleroy Ball's tenure as a consultant for the Hughes Aircraft Company.
- Hughes Aircraft Company--Printed Material 1955-1959, n.d., 21 items
- Miscellaneous 1951-1961, n.d., 5 items
- Miscellaneous Correpsondence 1879-1960, 24 items
  - re: [Frederick William Mackey Holliday] and accusations made against him in the Whigs' press during the Funding Acts controversy 1879 Mar 12
  - from the War Department re: Revolutionary War service of Isaac Hite 1893 Mar 3
  - Thomas Fauntleroy Ball to Franklin Delano Roosevelt re: communist and fascist tendencies in U.S. education 1940 Aug 28
  - Franklin Delano Roosevelt to Thomas Fauntleroy Ball 1940 Sep 6
  - James Forrestal, Secretary of the Navy, re: Thomas Fauntleroy Ball's World War II military service 1946 Nov 22
  - Warren Olney, III, Assistant Attorney General, re: letter from Thomas Fauntleroy Ball to Dwight David Eisenhower 1953 Feb 18
- Miscellaneous Printed Material 1921-1958, n.d., 6 items
- Naval Records of Thomas Faunteleroy Ball 1940-1956, 89 items
  Records Thomas Fauntleroy Ball's career on active and reserve duty. Includes correspondence, printed material, and documents establishing his date of birth (see letter, July 30, 1953).
- Naval Selection Board Guide [ca. 1952], 1 volume
  Regulations governing the Naval Selection Board, on which Thomas Fauntleroy Ball served.
- Personal Papers of Thomas Fauntleroy Ball 1940, 1952-1954, n.d., 9 items
- Photographs 1953, 1959, n.d., 8 items
  One photograph of G[eorge] Washington Ball, date is unclear.
- Southern California Industry -- Education Conference 1957, 1 volume
- Certificate from University of Virginia to Mary M. O. Veneable 1879 Apr 24-26
- Virginina law license of Cornelius H. Fauntleroy 1885 Jul 15
- Appointment of Robert R[andolph] Ball to position of assistant surgeon, signed by Grover Cleveland and by Secretary of War William C. Endicott 1887 Mar 7
- Diploma from American Institute of Electrical Engineering to Thomas Fauntleroy Ball 1928 Jan 23
- South Carolina electrical engineering license of Thomas Fauntleroy Ball 1930 Jul 8
- Diploma from American Institute of Electrical Engineering to Thomas Fauntleroy Ball 1938 Apr 22
- Broadside from Virginia chapter of Sigma Xi 1942 Apr 7
- Photograph and list of Navy personnel, including Thomas Fauntleroy Ball n.d.